hey folks welcome to the 12th
Dark Horse podcast livestream I am here
with dr. Heather highing
we are going to engage in a discussion
today of whether or not we have crossed
an event horizon let us first take care
of a few matters arising we are going to
be talking for about an hour and then we
are going to do a separate Q&A as has
worked much better for us in the past we
will answer your super chat questions as
filed during this live stream it will
get through as many of them as we can
and then we will collect some of the
super chat questions that are generated
during the Q&A other announcements that
we should make oh you want to talk so we
put your patreon e oh yes there has been
some question amongst fans of the
podcast about whether or not the
lectures that I have advertised on
patreon lectures is probably the wrong
word but the monthly discussions of
what's called the coalition of the
reasonable that's a politically focused
discussion and the evolutionary
discussion that follows first Saturday
and Sunday of each month and the
question is are they still running and
yes they are running they are quite
popular and exciting and we've been
having a great time there's some people
who've been participating in those
discussions for years now and anyway
they're very rewarding I have been a
little reluctant to push them because I
am reluctant about patreon itself after
it has demonstrated a desire to censor
people so I have not loved using their
mechanism that said no good substitute
has shown up and so for the moment
that's what we're using if you want to
join those discussions I think you would
find them very interesting okay so let's
see where are we I guess here's where we
are
I am wrestling with the fact that never
in my wildest imagination did I think
that the thing that was going to bring
humanity together was
to be the need for a haircut just didn't
see that coming
no that didn't show up in my accounting
either yeah so that raises the question
about whether or not we are across an
event horizon totally unpredictable
cause for global unity has shown up that
suggests that nobody's crystal ball is
all that clear at this moment so in this
case being across the event horizon
means we have gotten to a place where we
are completely unable to predict what
will happen next yes we have crossed
into a zone that could not have been
predicted from from before so anyway
that I mean sure that's tongue-in-cheek
but at some level it does seem to
characterize an awful lot of the
discussions we are having these days I
have lots of people telling me they're
sure this won't happen they're sure that
won't happen and I can't say that I'm
sure very much about what's going to
happen because this was just simply not
scheduled to happen this way so you're
specifically talking about what will
happen next or ultimately as opposed to
what do we think is true about the virus
and the response to it what's been
effective what's not what what might we
be doing to get any better result in the
future those those that second set of
things is not your including in the way
past the event horizon question is that
right yeah I would say there are certain
issues that I consider I had to hesitate
to say it almost mundane you know the
fact of the corona virus pandemic sure
there are details of it that are nothing
but surprising but the fact that some
zoonotic disease was going to emerge
from somewhere that we would the
awareness of its power and danger would
be too slow for us to react properly we
would treat it as a normal phenomenon
rather than the thing that we had been
told to fear so all of that I consider
relatively predictable what wasn't
predictable from my perspective is what
the dynamics that unfold in the
aftermath would look like I mean for
example the way it is interacting with a
presidential year here in the United
States and the party politics that
usually govern that is very surprising
so we now have a president who is I
would say pretty clearly incapable of
doing two things that are needed from
him at the moment one of them is
grappling with the scientific
complexities here at a level that would
be necessary to marshal a really proper
response and the other is he doesn't
seem to be able to put politics aside
but it sounds like you just said that
you wouldn't have predicted that I
really you wouldn't have predicted that
from this or many other presidents years
ago I would have predicted that
potentially for this president although
the thing that surprises me most maybe
and maybe I really just have no right to
be surprised by it but I keep thinking
that it should dawn on a Trump that he
has the opportunity to be a hero that
the thing he seems to crave about about
adulation and all he could have in
spades if he could simply adopt a new
mode that we haven't seen yet and I
think it's just really not in him but
what does surprise me is that in light
of these dynamics that the Democratic
Party is not marshalling a credible
alternative and therefore that we are
stuck in a predicament where we have an
incredibly feeble Democratic nominee who
obviously is going to be nominated but I
say obviously is going to be nominated
and I must say most of me doesn't
believe he's going to be nominated even
though that's the way it's supposed to
work how he will not be nominated is
unclear who might step in in lieu of Joe
Biden I think is also unclear because
obviously Bernie Sanders would be the
obvious choices that runner up but the
whole reason that we're stuck with Biden
is that the Democratic Party really
doesn't want and I don't mean the
Democratic Party like us Democrats I
mean the Democratic Party establishment
really doesn't want Bernie sander
he whatever else he may do he threatens
actual change about things that they're
trying to prevent change of so I guess
I'm a little surprised that you're
surprised that you're disappointed in
the Democratic National Committee at
this point having been you know we lived
together through the 2016 election in
which you were often apoplectic at what
the Democratic Party was doing as was i
but I think before this became the
global pandemic
and global governmental response that it
is both you and I had looked with
astonishment at the winnowing of a once
incredibly large like stupidly large
field of potential candidates in the
Democratic field and thought about many
of them no no way
no thank you and thought about a few of
them a very few of them oh hey that
might work and watch does it winnowed
and winnow tin winnowed and the heir
apparent became the same ol same ol this
all happened before you know at the
point that probably we should have
already been having responses at the
federal level within this country but we
didn't so the fact that there doesn't
seem to be any change now
within the Democratic National Committee
the DNC in terms of its response it
doesn't surprise me maybe I'm maybe I'm
done being surprised well you know
you're right well how what right do I
have to be surprised as the guy who's
usually pointing out that a we have
options we don't register and that be
the system is unsalvageable as it is
that we have to take drastic action so
at some level I guess part of me can't
be surprised but yeah well I think what
stuns me is that I see nothing creative
in the Democrats response here I see
nothing new I see I see a test in the
midst of kovat 19 I see a test of the
hypothesis that the problem with Hillary
Clinton was the pantsuit
I see a male Hillary Clinton who's
mentally what do you say that again
that's very hard to parse well I think
it's a preposterous if you thought that
Hillary Clinton just I'm not even sure
that the words made sense in that order
I think they did but would you say it
again sure if you thought that Hillary
Clinton was the right candidate but 4x
and X was up America wasn't ready for a
pantsuit right then you might try you're
just saying that this code for a female
president isn't oh I'm saying if you had
some dumb idea that it was some
triviality about the scenario and what
you wanted to do was run the identical
scenario with against an incumbent this
time and with the one little arbitrary
thing changed that you had imagined it
caused the problem in the first place
rather than recognizing that whatever
else may be true Hillary Clinton may
have won the popular vote but she didn't
slam dunk it a lot of people really
didn't want to vote for Hillary Clinton
and so the point is the problem was
never the pantsuit or anything arbitrary
the problem was that this was the same
DNC nonsense that people were fed up
with and so they're gonna try that again
in 2020 I believe we are basically in
the same class but I'm gonna push back
against the idea that the pantsuit is
the difference between Biden and Clinton
I didn't by then and I don't buy now you
know I didn't buy them that it was
widespread misogyny that kept Clinton
from the presidency and I don't buy now
that widespread misogyny is what kept
Elizabeth Warren who until she went woke
I thought was a pretty awesome candidate
but the fact is that there are there is
one large difference at least between
Clinton and Biden and if you know it's
not just the fancy not the dementia well
so yeah obviously she's she's more
competent still yes she and maybe she
wasn't then but at this point she's more
confident because she doesn't have scars
we know have any dementia and I you know
certainly there are a few people and I
honestly don't know if it's a fraction
of 1% or 10% of the population of this
country who wouldn't vote for a woman
for president but I'd be shocked it was
more than 10%
this point you know I'm not saying that
this is a credible idea I'm saying what
I'm watching is a Democratic Party
engaged in a live-fire exercise where
they test a wrong hypothesis about why
Hillary Clinton was not elected and they
test it by running a version of the same
politics dressed up differently I don't
care that she's a woman I don't think
most people care that Hillary Clinton is
a woman I think what we care about if
she represents the same thing that has
been parasitizing us for just over a
decade
isn't that in fact exactly what then is
being revealed the Democratic National
Committee cares about as well like that
that the status quo the establishment
politician is what they want to push on
us no matter what that's what's been
revealed well what they want is no
meaningful change the Democratic Party
that is quite at the point that it
abandoned the working class and embraced
a certain cadre of rent-seeking elites
basically became hostile to the idea of
change and in order to explain why we
should elect them if they're not
interested in change they've given us a
lot of symbolism hence the the woke
nightmare that we have seen sweep over
much of the left but still I would have
imagined no matter how dumb and
delusional the DNC may be I would have
thought they would have learned more
from 2016 than they apparently learned
and to find Joe Biden who is I think it
would be impossible to be enthusiastic
about this candidacy to find him as the
offering that we are being delivered in
the midst yeah okay this whole thing
didn't you know most of the presidential
primary did not unfold with our
awareness of Kovan 19 but nonetheless it
is a stunning moment to see our
political structure declare itself
incapable of finding a good president
right it has declared that on both sides
in in my opinion and what I would say if
we can get back to the event horizon
issue
is that okay if both sides have
delivered you an answer that is
unacceptable and then the world has
delivered you a crisis that reveals how
dangerous it is to have somebody in that
office who is not up to the challenge
then it seems to me this is the moment
at which we get to ask the question well
what possibilities that have seemed
impossible are now back on the table
what are you proposing well I'll go back
to proposing mutiny which is to say that
I don't know what opportunities we
actually have but I will say the
democratic party may not be salvageable
by virtue of the stranglehold on power
that the DNC appears to hold over it and
so there's a question about well if you
needed to storm the cockpit what other
mechanisms exist right is there
something that can be done and I don't
think this is the place to necessarily
explore that question but I think the
question needs to be on the table
because I think an awful lot of people
who are experiencing lockdown at home
will recognize that the system has
failed them and that every four years we
get a chance to alter how it functions
at a significant level well it could
instead though I mean I'm prepared to do
all sorts of different things than this
and I'm not prepared to answer your
question that you just launched you know
what is it that we do if we're going to
storm the cockpit because it's not clear
to me that that's where we are and what
we should be doing so it feels a little
bit like a setup but one way to approach
this where it doesn't feel like a setup
is to say okay if this is all very
standard sort of game theoretic outcomes
from a two-party system that has been
more and more cemented in place over the
course of decades
by some measures centuries and you might
call that as you have and has others
have game a maybe we should be talking
about what it would mean to move into a
game be universe maybe maybe that is the
setup that you are actually bringing to
us here well I think so
but I think you know for those of you
who are not aware of what game B means
game that's what that's that's what I'm
trying to set you up to describe because
I don't I don't think that a totally
abstract store in the cockpit is is
going to result in much further
discussion right here in fact you said
I'm not sure I want to continue that but
you know what what then what might we do
well how might we understand this as
okay maybe beyond their event horizon
it's really hard to predict now what's
gonna happen next
even on questions where it seems like
don't we have enough information no we
actually we seem to not because things
are changing so fast so how is it that
this very modern predicament of change
that is so fast that the future will not
look like the past how can we take that
situation and understand it in the
context of if game a is how things have
always been done how might we do things
in a different way
well one thing to say is that we we are
handed a system that has a structure
written into the Constitution and then
we are handed a system that functions
within it which is the parties which
hold on to power and they allocate it in
various ways and they make sure not to
lose it in other ways and the question
really is in light of the constitutional
structure that we have do we have
opportunities if we recognize that the
parties are not the route to good
governance so game B for what it's worth
is the idea that within the system there
are mechanisms that could create
desirable change could increase the
stability the antifragility
of the system the fairness of the system
that do not require something like the
taking a part of the constitutional
structure so I would say in fact really
there's no advocacy for that right that
the you know the extent the outline of
the constitutional structure in our
country remains what it has always been
which was farsighted and you know
simultaneously honouring of what has
worked in the past and open to novelty
moving forward in terms of solution
making well yeah I certainly I would say
you know the Constitution the matically
is right I would say like any document
that was written when it was it's
incapable of handling many of the 21st
century realities so you know I don't
think we should treat it as sacred
though I do think that in terms of a the
founders would have had a hard time
doing better given what they understood
and be in light of the values that they
enshrined in it I don't think we should
be eager to open it up but I do think
beyond that I would be afraid to see it
opened up because I think it would be a
political disaster and we would end up
making the Constitution far worse so
anyway if you take that or some position
like it as correct then the question is
well what can we do within the structure
that would usher in the proper style of
changes without an alteration to the the
underlying foundation and the first
place I mean I guess what I would say is
look it's 2020 we have an opportunity
upcoming that opportunity isn't as big
as it might be because the primary
season has already run its course but
there may be an opportunity if Biden is
not viable by virtue of the accusations
that have been brought against him then
what happens next I'm not sure I know
buddy and I know anybody who knows the
answer to that question so again it's an
event horizon of some kind yes
the
the remarkable convergence of global
pandemic increasing dementia and are
they credible nobody seems to agree
allegations of sexual possibly even
crimes in the past of this candidate
coming together leads no one as far as I
can tell with an ability to accurately
guess as to what happens what happens
next I haven't I haven't seen it anyway
yeah haven't seen it exactly so that's
really all I'm saying is let us at least
recognize that we're in that moment
right and therefore all sorts of things
that get said under normal circumstances
about what can't happen and what you
mustn't do with respect to how you cast
your vote all sorts of things must now
be on the table because all of the
things that are supposed to give us some
normal choice that we're supposed to
vote for without thinking too hard about
it
didn't work they led us to a remarkable
situation of amazing vulnerability a
choice between two unacceptable outcomes
so maybe that's where we should leave it
it's okay all right
you've had some things that you wanted
to to raise from the recent week well
you know I don't know I was sort of
gonna integrate it with our conversation
but I'm not sure I'm not sure that
anything's integratable with that maybe
maybe this to start I guess that we do
see more of the same more of the same
gobbledygook sort of pre-modern thinking
coming out of the so-called right and
postmodern thinking coming out of the
so-called left and I know there are many
good people on the right who reject the
pre modernism that that is sometimes
conflated with the entire right and
certainly there are many people on the
Left who reject the postmodern garbage
that comes out of what is often
conflated with the entire left so maybe
it's just you know it's shooting fish in
a barrel at some levels a little bit too
easy but the examples are always fun
because they're so ridiculous so
should we go should we should we talk
about an example of a Republican Ohio
state lawmaker first or Politico
publishing about how hard this is all on
women let's go with the Politico let's
go with Politico first okay so over in
what the hell is the left doing now
narrative we have Politico actually I
can pull this hold on Zack yeah here it
is now you can show it on screen
Politico nightly coronavirus special
edition kovetz war on women during this
plague year there was almost never good
news only degrees of bad news even so
the pandemic has been different and
worse for girls and women it's true the
article continues it's true that more
men are dying than women from kovat 19
around the world but that's not exactly
cause for celebration
I think I'm insulted Wow so I would just
draw everyone's attention in case it
wasn't clear to you the word but in that
last sentence it's true that more men
are dying than women from koban 19
around the world but that's not exactly
cause for celebration how could you
possibly write that and at least one of
the authors is a man himself really
truly remarkable and I don't know what
else there is to say except with these
people please stop calling themselves
progressives and on the left for the
sake of all of us who would like to do
good and not be stuck in traditions that
are out of date nothing
it's remark oh I mean I don't notice the
I don't know how such a thing it
diagnoses the system the very fact of
that piece having gotten through with
that wording suggesting that there might
be something positive about men dying at
a higher rate certainly does but it
doesn't go far enough to be worth
celebrate
don't know what the claim is here but
just the idea that that this ostensibly
journalistic outfit contains enough
people to read that over to get it on
line without
anybody's saying wait what did we just
say maybe it's impossible to raise that
complaint maybe somebody did see it and
realized it was objectionable but you
can't say so within the confines of
Politico well and that's I mean that
that's going to be right and that that
points to some of the problems that
we've talked about here before and
that's certainly your brother has talked
about with regard to in this case it is
you know what happens not at the you
know the you know how do you get how do
you get into academia or how do you get
into the media but within media outlets
there becomes no matter what it is an
orthodoxy that you shall not speak
against and certainly we can all name
outlets on both the left and the right
that appear to have an orthodoxy outside
of which nothing shall be spoken and
probably there are a couple of those I
hope on both sides that are actually
working from the inside to try to expand
what kinds of opinions are are speakable
but this idea that no matter what the
story is we will and we must put a spin
on it that turns it into a way to point
out that the world is sexist and the
world is racist and let's just continue
on with it's you know we've already
talked before about how God what I don't
member which outlet was wired that claim
that it's not obesity that is a risk but
it's it's fat shaming mm-hm
right so is that is that sizes I don't
even know what the word is right but so
there's you know there's there's that
ideology ingrained so much in some of
these outlets on and I won't always want
you scare quotes on the so-called left
that it's it actually seems impossible
to escape their poll well I don't know
whether to interject this here or to
wait for your next example
maybe I'll just interject it here and
then we can go to the next example but
the there is a second epidemic
the second epidemic has to do with the
inability to step out of one's political
identity and viewpoint
and into neutral space and the problem
with something like a global pandemic of
a zoonotic disease or something like it
is that it is not a political phenomenon
inherently it is a fact and it requires
a dispassionate apolitical frankly
patriotic response that we're talking at
the national level and then whatever the
equivalent of patriotism is to the globe
if we're talking at a higher level but
we patriotic being distinct from
nationalistic yes I draw a distinction
and patriotic involves sacrifice for
some larger entity like your nation but
in this case we have a a question that
we have to ask ourselves so we're
watching for example these protesters
who are demanding that we remove the
lockdown and some of them explicitly and
some of them implicitly are effectively
making an argument about the comparison
between the costs of the lockdown and
the cost of the deaths that will occur
if we lift it now some of them are in
denial about whether there is a hazard
to begin with but if we put those ideas
aside there is a calculation to be made
obviously we do these calculations all
the time you want to eliminate all
highway deaths that's easy you just end
driving all right we don't do that
because we all figure that the cost of
the ability to drive is worth the fact
that there will be some deaths but one
thing that is true is that most members
of the public always Blanche when the
actuarial analysis is brought into stark
relief right the the fact how much
you're paying for life insurance or to
some degree health insurance is in fact
based on exactly these kinds of
actuarial actuarial analyses about how
long you're expected to live based on
how healthy or and what kinds of
decisions you make and the last time I
remember actually and I'm probably
forgetting
in the interim but the last time I
remember sort of public outcry over the
idea of a value being placed on a human
life was in the wake of 9/11 when it
became clear that cash was it was it the
government who was paying families of
those killed in the twin towers and in
the few other places where people died
directly in one of those are from one of
those for plans people who had made more
during their lives are being paid more
and there was an outcry without a
recognition that actually this is the
kind of analysis that's happening all
the time everywhere and just completely
putting aside whether or not that is as
it should be it certainly is and it
certainly works within an economic
system that is not frankly inherently
predatory at that level yes and you know
the problem is that we politeness keeps
us from having the discussions that we
need to have about what what really is
fair why certain lives count more than
others mean for example you know should
we work harder to prevent the death of a
young person than an old person almost
certainly yes right it's very easily
defended what I think is unfolding here
that's very unfortunate and it may be an
example of exactly what we've been
talking about for several previous live
streams is the unfolding of dangerous
game theory yeah and the problem is
you've got what should be what's called
in philosophy of rauzein veil of
ignorance which is you don't want to
make a rule that you wouldn't want to
live on the wrong side of so it's sort
of the adult version of I divided you
choose if you want to make only rules
that you would be willing to be
subjected to rather than rules that
favor you and disfavor somebody else
yeah I've never heard it described that
way before that's that's very good all
right
but in any case the problem is here we
know an awful lot about who is
vulnerable to this disease and therefore
the danger that people who for whatever
reason don't feel vulnerable don't have
vulnerable people in there
close circle and their family or
something like that have an incentive to
demand a lifting of the the lockdown I
don't know how many people will have
seen Caitlyn Flanigan's piece in the
Atlantic I think it came out today did
you see it no it's a just terrific and
she is terrific and it's a very
heart-wrenching piece she describes her
own battle with cancer and the fact that
it makes her very very vulnerable to
this this pathogen and anyway she talks
about some things that we had close to
home for us about the cancellation of
her son's graduation which he had been
you know she's counting the years that
she's made it from diagnosis and he was
going to make a graduation if he never
thought she'd see and then suddenly it's
canceled
it's it's a it's a tragic piece but in
any case there's a question we have to
look at ourselves let's just limit this
to the American context for the moment
we have to look at ourselves and we have
to say are we the sort of people who are
going to recognize that there's a
category of folks who are very
vulnerable and say well we're gonna lose
those but that's okay or are we not are
we going to say that in this case
actually those people ended up unlucky
they ended up in a in a vulnerable
category with respect to this but those
of us who feel less vulnerable to this
thing frankly it's a prosperous enough
Society that we can actually afford to
not throw them overboard and you know
this is I think where I come out which
is that this is not a calculation of how
many deaths is acceptable not to wreck
the economy the problem is we know an
awful lot about where those deaths are
going to land and that runs the risk of
the tyranny of the majority of the
majority of people who are not so
vulnerable inflicting this on a bunch of
people who did nothing more to deserve
it
than we did
you know I think a prosperous society
doesn't have to make that choice a
prosperous society is de facto making
that choice though given that the social
safety net seems to be broken and
riddled with holes and it doesn't have
to have but you know for all of the you
how many trillions of dollars did the
cares package Chara's Act have and
promised 1200 people to every adult
making $75,000 or less in 2018 and five
hundred more for the kids and additional
I think six hundred a week federally for
unemployment and on top of whatever the
state is giving that all sounds like
that should be could be for people
making that amount of income or less
unless they were living way outside of
their means in the first place like way
it a way over-indebted like that that
could could and should be enough if I
think if everything else is in place and
we are hearing so many stories of people
not receiving their checks being told
actually you're not going to receive it
until you until you do your taxes next
year not even this year but next year
and the number of stories about you know
small businesses who are in a damned if
you do damned if you don't situation
because they can get some money but then
they have to spend it all very quickly
or else they risk having to pay it back
and I mean just the people are having to
make impossible choices because the
bureaucracy in place is not acting like
safety net it's acting like bureaucracy
so I agree with you exactly and I would
just point out that this is in some
sense I think why the political
apparatus is fumbling this so badly
right when this should be a non
political issue that could be handled
well and would turn anyone who did
handle it well into a hero the problem
is that this once you start getting into
this question about you know why are
people who are weak from illness going
to be thrown under the bus so that those
who aren't so weak can go back to living
a normal life
you do start getting into questions
about well why why is the unfairness
distributed the way it is under normal
circumstances and some of it is for
legitimate reasons but a lot of it isn't
right there is a lot of our system that
simply reinforces patterns of well-being
that already exist which means we've got
echoes of all kinds of arbitrary and not
so arbitrary patterns from the past that
do continue forward and we could for the
same reasons that I would argue we
should not throw vulnerable people under
the bus to Cove at 19 that we actually
this is a time to for us collectively to
spend to protect them that same question
exists on a normal day when there's no
pandemic by virtue of the fact that why
are we gonna let this community suffer
right when in fact the reasons that it
is you know what the reason that it is
vulnerable have to do with decisions
that it didn't have any part in either
so I do think it would be marvelous
if this moment got us to sideline our
politics enough that we could have a
courageous discussion about those
questions and you know as I've argued
elsewhere luck is really the enemy right
good and bad luck are noise when it
comes to the things to create well-being
a fair system minimizes the role of luck
and outcomes yeah this is this is what
you've said in the past and I think I
don't know if you said it exactly that
way but that's that's how I've
internalized it a fair system minimizes
the role of luck in the outcomes of
people such that they are maximally free
to produce to create to live to the best
of their abilities and desires yep and
then that actually be by virtue of the
fact that it eliminates noise it creates
signal that guides you tells you what's
actually worth doing because you get
rewarded for things that actually create
good in the world so we want a system
that has positive feedback motivational
structures built-in yeah rather than the
series of negative feedback motivational
structures that start at kindergarten
all right and pretty much contain
you know at least through retirement if
not beyond given at least in the u.s.
that people continue to have to deal
with things like Medicare and and
retirement plans
yeah beyond that absolutely yeah
so having mocked the pseudo left shall
we mock the I don't know if I want to
call it the pseudo right this is at
least the reflection of one person who
is on the right but I know it does not
reflective of what everyone on the right
thanks yes yes yes we should let's mocks
ridiculous right ridiculous right okay
Zack put this up this is in Newsweek
headline Republican Ohio state lawmaker
refuses to wear face masks because God
created humans without one hmm okay so
I'm gonna read a quote from this article
on his Facebook page vitaly said he
would defy the requests of his states
governments on religious ground this is
not the entire world Vitaly wrote this
is the greatest nation on earth founded
on judeo-christian principles one of
those principles is that we are all
created in the image and likeness of God
that image is seen the most by our face
I will not wear a mask when we think
about the image and likeness of God were
created in the image and likeness of God
and we think of image do we think of a
chest or a legs or arms we think of a
face that's the image of God right there
and I want to see it in my brothers and
sisters you know I think he may actually
have a kind of a point but I would
suggest that taken to its logical
conclusion you will also recognize that
God created people without pants
yep under or otherwise he seems to be
arguing for everyone to walk around in
what used to be called their birthday
suits yes yeah exactly so anyway yeah
that is I mean let's put it this way if
we take God out of the equation there is
something to be said for the fact that
your face is a specially built
communication apparatus in humans and
that denying people the ability to
communicate with their face is you know
I think it's actually one of the
strongest arguments against things like
a burqa is that you're denying people
the ability to communicate on the other
hand there's a very good reason in this
case that we would be doing at an
epidemiological reason
that is protective of the people wearing
the masks as much as anyone else I mean
I do think I don't know how many people
have sort of sorted through what parts
of wearing a mask make them
uncomfortable I don't know that anyone
likes it right and you know put aside
those people who already masked for
religious reasons like religious Muslim
women but now that many of us are
walking around masked when we go outside
well you know when we go into stores and
when we are inside with strangers most
of us many of us I hope most of us are
wearing masks now and yet I don't I
haven't heard from anyone that they kind
of are liking that you know it's an it's
an ability to explore fashion or like I
don't know that anyone likes it but how
many people are actually exploring what
is it that they don't like there's
social pressure that until so in one of
our local markets now mandates masks if
you're going to come in and that takes a
social pressure out because when you're
walking around everyone else in the
store is masked and there is no inherent
judgement whereas just you know a mile
down the road there's another store
where it's not mandatory and they're the
social distinction is still happening
and there's people judging and making
political assessments based on whether
you're masked and whether you're not but
but this this other issue and I'm sure
there's more than two but the two that
come well 3 maybe
so social pressure discomfort physical
discomfort and for some people it's
actually real people with actual
respiratory problems asthma as such may
actually have a harder time breathing
through a mask right yeah so there's
there's that and you know and if the
weather is very hot it's actually going
to be potentially stifling dogs your
glasses oh my god I'm starting I wear my
contacts when I go out and also I don't
plug my glasses but the third thing
which is what which is what you raised
here and which if we take if we take
this Republican Ohio state lawmaker if
we take the religion out of it and
through the pre-modern wooowww out of it
and say well actually what is the value
then in walking around with bare faces
it's huge
this is exactly
we communicate and it's you know this is
this is one of the reasons I hate phones
so much right but that having voice only
is not sufficient it is not sufficient
to actually do the full job of human
communication yeah I agree with that I
had an incident at one of our markets I
was in there checking out and I was
being hold on a second this is the one
with the mandatory masks are one of the
ones I think there's only one don't
think it was a shame this is a news
market it's not very well traveled um
but anyway I was checking out and I was
being my usual ironic self and because
my face was covered the guy was talking
to who it turned out later in the
conversation was very much up for having
a kind of you know dialogue that would
involve wit and things like that
couldn't tell that I was kidding and
anyway it kind of made the conversation
very awkward at first and then you know
I guess maybe I'm just learning how to
engage in that behavior with the with
the mask but well this is actually I
think perfectly analogous to one of the
problems with with social media that we
were reduced it seems like we're doing
writing but it's more like we're in this
sort of and this has been argued by
scholars of language that we're sort of
returning to something that's more like
an oral culture and we mostly are
playing don't know how to play the rule
play by the rules and so I actually
think that you've run afoul of this a
few times with regard to you have a code
right you know just stop me or correct
me if I get this wrong but as I
understand it now you have a code and
it's that if you use an emoji it means
you're being sarcastic or ironic or
otherwise saying something that you
really really don't mean and so it
should be read that way right it's
effectively it's it's the you know you
can do it with your facial expressions
although you also do a good job of
keeping a straight face so that you
could lead people down a primrose path
Walker in person but you know in a tweet
for instance I now know that when I see
an emoji associated
something that you've written that you
don't mean it I might also know what
your positions are for the most part but
I think that today for instance you I
don't remember even what you said but
you but you put a radio or something put
a radio emoji next to it I thought no
one is gonna get this yes I said free
speech doesn't mean you can just say
whatever you want right which I think
the words in and of themselves can note
irony either you're an idiot
or they can note irony but I what I find
on Twitter is again and again when I say
something like that which I feel is so
over-the-top that everybody will have
two hundred I mean maybe it won't be
their first thought but their second
thought will be maybe he's kidding I
guess middle it's so in the middle of
what some of what many people think I
know that's the beauty right but so
you're saying it's over the top yeah you
and but you also recognize that the
beauty of it as you say is that it's
smack dab in the middle of the ideology
that says it's not exactly cause for
celebration
that more men are dying than women right
so that ideology people who buy into
that ideology would absolutely say the
thing that you said and it's it requires
it requires eyebrows it requires facial
structure requires that you be
interacting in real-time probably
without a mask in order to make sure
that your audience knows first time that
that was actually not what you really
believe in your heart of hearts well I
don't know see I mean I guess the whole
problem is you know for me this is sort
of where humor is it's you know it's the
ultimate teaching tool which doesn't
mean that you know it's a somber thing
it's obviously tremendous fun but what I
want is for people who resonate with the
idea that you know free speech doesn't
mean you can say whatever you want I
want them to say yeah and then say wait
what what did I just say that doesn't
make any sense
you know so anyway we've we've lost this
in part text isn't great at this
especially you know as you've pointed
out in our classes where we knew our
students really really well you could
use irony
you you know to upgrade the software and
you know you've pointed to the setting
man works better when you know who
you're talking do you know who you talk
to exactly so you you mentioned this
thing that I used to do all the time
with students where if students if we
were on a field trip let's say and
students were goofing off and they were
sitting you know I saw a group of
students at a table you know laughing it
up I would walk over and in a completely
serious tone of voice with no expression
on my face I'd say guys if you're
laughing you're not learning and that
table would go deadly and then you know
the first person at the table to get the
joke would be like wait a minute what
are you saying and then you know and
then it sort of dawns I mean I actually
believe almost exactly the opposite if
you're laughing you probably are
learning also if you're crying it works
either way but the point is these if you
did not however ever aim to nor I think
really ever actually make students cry
it probably has a voice but but anyway
yeah so anyway these things are if you
do know the person really well then it
works out on Twitter we all only kind of
know each other and so it doesn't work
out at all so yes I've resorted to if
there's an emoji then this is not to be
taken at face value whoops
in this case it's gonna continue asking
about this what's with the radio emoji
how does that possibly be so I'm always
just like I mean just kind of looks like
you hit a random button before hitting
send no first of all I do not commit
myself that the emoji will be
content-rich though I always look for
one that is instead of pronouns and your
buyer you need this if emoji then
sarcasm sarcasm right but the radio
actually was chosen because the thing I
was responding to was Jay Shapiro asking
the question in earnest I think about if
Alex Jones has been evicted from all of
these platforms does he have free speech
and so anyway radio seemed relevant but
you know kind of all right you got to
work with me a little bit on the emoji
thing okay
okay I think we're done picking
ridiculous examples from the right and
the left with regard to how they're
responding to this crisis you won't talk
a little bit about the varying responses
to well I guess the good segue here is
people are becoming politicized over
lockdown versus no lockdown which is
once again a false choice it's a false
dichotomy there's it shouldn't be a
binary because many governments clearly
as we talked about a little bit last
time the numbers are showing that
lockdowns are effective in reducing
deaths but there is also a good argument
a conversation important conversation to
be had with regard to what are the other
effects and therefore what number of
deaths are we willing to put up with etc
but I think frankly for me the more
interesting question is not lockdowns
versus not lockdowns
but what kind of lockdowns what what
kinds of injunctions are coming down
from governments be they city state
province national that at some point
those who are most firmly behind the
idea of lockdowns who really understand
why masks matter why social distancing
matters all of this are going to stop
are going to start breaking rules
because many of the roles that are being
handed down to us are ridiculous and bad
and are not based on a sell
understanding of what's going on so just
a few examples
I mean we've we've already talked about
this but it looked for a little while
last week before what was supposed to be
our last livestream and sorry guys
technical troubles stop that but it
looked like governor Newsom in
California was going to shut down all
parks and beaches across the state which
is ridiculous right it's an totally
ridiculous response turns out I don't
know if he really was or he wasn't but
he got so much pushback before it ever
happened that actually was just just the
Orange County beaches which is in Orange
County for those not familiar with
California is
giant County in Southern California
basically between LA and San Diego I
think right it's the it's the only
coastal county between LA County and San
Diego County and you know frankly it
also feels a little bit like a political
move because la is pretty blue and San
Diego is pretty blue aside from maybe
the military bases and Orange County is
pretty red all right it's it's one of
the coastal California counties in you
know that's south of Golden Gate Bridge
that runs Republican so it may be felt a
little personal a little political and
well what do you know what do you think
well first of all I want to this
dovetails a lot with what I've been
thinking about over the last week and I
want to put a little amplifier on the
point it's not ridiculous it's isn't
ridiculous the shutting down of the
public parks yeah it's actually
dangerous and it is making the exact
problem that it is supposed to be
solving worse and here's I want to be
careful about this because I think we
now have enough information to say that
with some certainty but the point is if
it's true it was true before we had the
information to say that was some
certainty yeah and so the things I'm
thinking of in particular with you and I
have discussed extensively on and off
air our a this thing seems to be very
difficult to transmit outdoors yeah we
talked about a couple of live streams
ago a result out of China that tracked
7,000 plus cases community transmission
cases rather than travel cases only one
maybe two of which were understood to
have been transmitted outdoors yeah so
what I would say is if you're trying to
think about what behavior to engage in I
would say being outdoors makes things
better and not worse obviously if you're
in a house with nobody who's got the
infection then your house is probably
pretty safe so going outdoors is not a
step in the right direction but it's
probably not too dangerous but if you
couple it with social distancing masks
and common sense then it may be that
there is in fact an opportunity cost to
not
going outdoors that the cost of being in
a building drives up your likelihood of
contracting the thing what would
eventually I mean in indoor air
pollution is a real thing so even put
aside if you live alone and you haven't
had anyone else in your house and so you
really know that the virus isn't in your
house that doesn't mean that the air in
your house is healthy to be breathing so
opening up windows getting outside
you'll having cross ventilation that's
not mechanical but is actually fresh and
natural is understood to have health
benefits regardless of what particular
pathogens or just particulate matter
that might be causing you know lung
issues might be around right which could
make you more vulnerable if a pathogen
does get through the door you encounter
it somewhere also lots of people even
people who do live alone or with family
members who don't have kovat 19 they
still live in a building that might
transmit it between compartments or
something but anyway what we're learning
now is that vitamin D looks like it may
have a protective effect um it may
prevent you from getting it and it
really seems very likely to reduce the
severity if you do get it so here's what
we I think are beginning to understand
going outside reduces the likelihood of
transmission it also increases your
ability to fend off the disease if you
do get it on the basis that vitamin D is
produced when UV light hits the skin
therefore to the extent that regulations
have said don't go out stay in your home
what they actually do is they create
vitamin D deficiencies because even if
it's in your food it's hard to get
enough of it that way the way we create
vitamin D involves effectively
photosynthesis of it that people whose
instinct was to go outside were safer
and laws that
scolded people for going outside you
mentioned one case in which people were
told not to sit in their garden there's
frontal ruk right that these things are
all counterproductive on the list of
things for how to protect yourself from
this disease should be sunlight exposure
to sunlight right do it
social distancing where your mask but go
outside so the me just put this up for I
know you have someplace else you're
going here but our friend Marsha Burke
be sent us this that in British Columbia
the instruction is in fact please go
outside
what is she the UC provincial Minister
of Health I believe says Cove in
nineteen is much less likely to spread
outdoors and please please please go
outside no social distance wear masks to
be around other people all of these
things but this is the only place that
I've seen actually an explicit directive
from a government official saying
actually we want you to do the opposite
of what everyone else is saying right
and then there's the final point which I
think we have no way to calibrate the
importance of at this point
but there is a question especially in
light of a very frightening scenario
that is unfolding that a to the degree
that anything normal can be safe enough
to engage in is mental health wise bound
to be a positive thing so how many
suicides will we prevent if people are
encouraged to go out to frankly know
that there are other people in the world
like physically be in their presence
without being in danger these things
have a very positive benefit and what's
frightening to me is if we to some
extent cancel some part of spring/summer
if we reduce people's ability to enjoy
the outdoors the way they do then what
happens to us as winter descends I
really think that this is a frightening
prospect in light of the fact that we
don't really see an endgame here if
there's a vaccine coming it's probably
year and a half two years or more off so
to the extent that we are in this for
the long haul
doing things that reduce the mental
hazard of it which seemed to be
epidemiologically safe and you know it's
nice out there
so anyway people whose instinct was to
go outside were right
government to the extent that it was
telling him to stay inside was wrong
that was true all along now the data is
beginning to tell us that so that is a
model for how the counterintuitive here
was a very important thing and I guess I
would add one more thing which is just
like the subway study that we discussed
I don't know maybe three livestreams ago
in which it became clear that New York
City's responds to Coba 19 which was to
try to enforce stay at home for people
was to ask them not to take the subway
and the what it's not the MTA but
whatever the Transit Authority in New
York City is responded by cutting back
the number of trains such that those
people who were on trains who were
forced to take trains because they were
essential workers for whatever reason
were then tightly packed and we're much
more likely to be effective ly spreading
the disease so having a public response
B we're going to create scarcity in
order to try to get you not to use this
resource forces higher density of people
and therefore higher risk to those
people who are using it so shutting down
a bunch of nature areas is and leaving a
few open as ends up being the case in I
think California is going to crunch
people into a few of the areas whereas
letting them spread out across an entire
landscape and make decisions for
themselves in this case in a place where
in a in a situation in which we
understood that we understand this to be
healthy transmission doesn't seem to
happen outdoors much and it's not just
healthy physically but also mentally to
go through the examples you were just
talking about the this is this is what
we should be doing and outdoors actually
becomes more dangerous the more tightly
packed you are right that's that that is
the condition under which being outdoors
is potentially more dangerous everywhere
becomes more dangerous everywhere
becomes more dangerous the more tightly
packed you are and so if you're going to
recognize that nature and outdoors is
actually safer than indoors leaving all
of that open for
people to explore and to be in and to be
hopefully making the same kinds of
careful decisions that they're making
when they go into the market or the
hardware store whatever it's clearly a
better move than saying well we're gonna
shut down some and not others and thus
force those of you who are feeling the
need to go outside into a smaller amount
of space and it also reflects something
that we've been getting at which is the
the governmental structure that wants to
dictate exactly what to do is feeble
compared to a structure that tells us
what the objective is and gives us room
to navigate yeah so I have argued every
functional complex system that involves
people also involves discretion so what
we really want is not a politicized
populace in which you know the folks on
the right are dismissive of the need to
take action and the folks on the left
are insisting on the action and all of
that what we need is a recognition that
we all are better off if this thing
doesn't spread further if the cost of it
is low because people are well prepared
and people have discretion to figure out
how to to enact the the counter measures
so to the extent that you're outside you
know you're not gonna have X's on the
ground that tell you where to stand
you know those X's aren't particularly
great anyway in the in the various
markets but if you understand the
principles if somebody's shown you an
animation of how the particle is
dispersed from somebody who's coughing
or talking or something like that then
you can steer clear of them in a way
that minimizes the chances of contacting
something so being informed and having
discretion to do what reaches the
objective rather than being nannied into
abiding by some rule that's yes stupidly
simple so you know exactly what it is
but leaves a lot of possible value
unexplored good I think we are about at
the our mark but I'd like to maybe just
flag what's happening in Manaus and
maybe we come back to it another time
I believe it was our fourth live stream
that we talked about Guayaquil the large
city in coastal Ecuador that's
experiencing really tragic response to
the corona virus and what's happening in
Manaus which is a city of two million
people in the middle of the Brazilian
Amazon is very similar and it looks like
it's going to become the next kill in
Latin America Zack if you would just
quickly put on screen this image which
is an aerial view of coffins being
buried an area where new graves have
been dug this is their experiencing it
was so we you talked last time about
this measure of the effect of SARS Cove
- as one of a good measures excess
deaths you know how you can take it down
now say how many more people died in a
particular area during a particular
period of time than did at the same
period of time in previous years for the
same area controls for so many things
that it really seems to to be a very
useful metric and it's obviously got it
potentially has error in both directions
but overall the idea of excess deaths of
tracking how many more deaths occurred
than we were expecting
is is a really apt one and in Manaus the
xxxx the excess deaths are - closing on
three times for the period of the last
six weeks or so and they they report
that it just showed up there in early
March of course none of these reports of
when it actually showed up in particular
places are necessarily accurate maybe
that's one of the things we'll talk
about next time but one of the problems
in Manaus Manaus is literally at the
confluence of the Amazon and there
which are to these massive rivers and
the Amazon just got the name afterwards
so everyone knows the name of the Amazon
and not the name of every renege row
there it's its place I've actually been
and fell in love with and really wanted
us to go back to and then we went had
kids instead so we haven't been back but
it's truly an extraordinary place it is
you know it's the sort of center of the
Brazilian Amazon and for a long time you
can only get there by boat or by plane
there is no a road unfortunately
fortunately but you know massive
bustling metropolis that is not in the
industrial center of Brazil in the South
you know Rio and Sao Paulo and for
taking there being the massive centers
of you know of economy for Brazil and
bolson ro but the president of Brazil
has long sent long before this
particular pandemic struck made it clear
that he sees the Amazon as a untapped
way to make money that he sees the
forest as mostly an impediment to
development and the indigenous peoples
as same and while Manaus is not you know
it's it's surrounded by forests and
there are indigenous tribes somewhat
near it it is not itself you know we
filled with indigenous people or
forested place it probably got ignored a
bit in part because this was already a
city and already a region in Brazil that
was not being treated well by the by the
governance yeah it's also the case that
early on there was the expectation and
based on a pattern that people had
thought they had seen where this wasn't
being spread in tropical climates and I
know that now in Manaus the question is
will they be the next quiet kill that
that's actually on their minds and the
fact that there is a man aus crisis ana
Guayaquil crisis says that whatever it
is that might be somewhat protective
about these climates it's not completely
protective and probably means very
little
most of us and go ocular sweltering hot
humid places right so I think as we are
and I really hope people will sideline
the political dimensions the question
about what we should do
mustn't be a political question the
question about where this came from also
must not be a political question and it
is becoming an unavoidable one so in any
case maybe we will return there another
time but for the moment we have
different outcomes based on different
kinds of responses a political actor
will cherry-pick that data in order to
support whatever policy position they
think is right the rest of us should be
looking at these things and thinking
well we know that New York can happen we
know that manaus and Guayaquil can
happen we know that Italy can happen
what we don't want to do is alter the
protocols so that you know la becomes
the next New York if that's possible we
want to learn from what has happened and
frankly share the burden of it the
political solution to this is no
solution at all and what it effectively
does is it puts the pathogen in charge
so really I can't stress enough how
important it is that we don't allow
politics to drive which then says
something about well how are we going to
reign on our politics because that's
exactly what they're setting us up for
that's right
okay so we are going to return in 15
minutes to another link which we will
put in the description of this video
where we will answer your super cat
questions anything else we should say
here subscribe if you like yes that's
right like subscribe hit the notify Bell
I don't know knock yourself out comment
below the stream here alright we'll see
you in very few minutes